Register of the George D. Stoddard Miscellaneous Papers, 1945-1980.
Hoover Institution Archives
George Dinsmore Stoddard Miscellaneous Papers
1945-1980
81023
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes, 1 album box, 1 envelope, 8 microfilm reels (5.1 linear feet)
Memoirs, correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, memoranda, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to the U.S. Education Mission to Japan, and to the subsequent development of Japanese education. Also available on microfilm (4 reels)
Stoddard, George Dinsmore, 1897-
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (4 reels)
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Contents note
Memoirs, correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, memoranda, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to the U.S. Education Mission to Japan, and to the subsequent development of Japanese education.
Biographical Note.
1897, October 8 Born, Carbondale, Pennsylvania
1921 A.B., Pennsylvania State College
1925 Ph.D., University of Iowa
1926-1928 Assistant Professor, University of Iowa
1928-1929 Associate Professor, University of Iowa
1929-1942 Professor, University of Iowa
1942-1946 Commissioner of Education, the University of the State of New York
1946 Chairman, United States Education Mission to Japan
1946-1953 President, University of Illinois
1956-1960 Dean, New York University, School of Education
1960-1964 Chancellor, New York University, School of Education
1964-1967 Distinguished Professor of Education, New York University
1967-1968 Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs, Long Island University
1968-1969 Chancellor, Long Island University
United States. Education Mission to Japan.; Education--Japan.; Education.; Japan.; United States--Foreign relations.
- Correspondence File, 1946-1970.
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence of George D. Stoddard, arranged alphabetically by correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1946-1952, 1980.
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches, articles, memoranda, and an autobiographical excerpt by George D. Stoddard, arranged alphabetically by title
- Subject File, 1945-1967.
  Notes, correspondence, reports, and printed articles, arranged alphabetically by subject
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1946-1970
  - General (Box 1)
  - Abe, Mikishi, 1946
  - Akatsuka, Yasuo, 1969-1970
  - Benton, William, 1946/1967
  - Edwards, J. Dixon, 1950
  - Japan. Ministry of the Imperial Household, 1946-1950
  - Mead, Margaret, 1946
  - Mitsuzumi, Keizo, 1950
  - Nabara, Shigeru, 1946-1951
  - Nugent, D. R., 1946-1950
  - Tanabe, Stefan, 1946-1950
  - Time, 1946
  - Waring, Ethel B., 1947
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, /1980, 1946-1952
  - "Are We Re-Educating the Germans and the Japanese?" (with Ernest Colwell and Edward D'Arms), Round Table, transcript of radio broadcast, 28. Printed copies, 1946 July (Box 1)
  - "The Education Mission to Japan: A Summary," Association of American Colleges Bulletin, Typescript and printed copies, 1946 October.
  - "MacArthur and the U.S. Education Mission to Japan," National Parent-Teacher, Typescript and printed copies, 1946 September.
  - Memorandum, re Japan at the end of World War II, Typescript
  - Memorandum, re conference with General MacArthur, 20. Typescript, 1946 March
  - "Mission to Japan," speech, Phi Delta Kappa, University of Illinois, 7. Typescripts, 1946 August
  - "A Note on Japanese Education," 22. Typescript, 1946 June
  - "The Pursuit of Education: An Autobiography," excerpt, Typescript (photocopy), ca. 1980.
  - "Reflections on Japanese Education," The Phi Delta Kappan, Typescript and printed copies, 1946 October.
  - Review of Elizabeth Vining, Windows for the Crown Prince, in The Horn Book Magazine, Printed copies, 1952 August.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1945-1967
  - Germany - Education (Box 1)
  - Japan
    - General
    - Book donations, 1947
    - Christian University
    - Constitution
    - Education
      - 1945-1949
      - 1950-1959
      - 1960-1967 (Box 2)
    - Souvenir booklets
    - Writing system
  - Miscellaneous
  - Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers (SCAP)
    - General
    - Education in Japan, 15, 1946 February
    - Education in Japan, I, 1948 May
    - Education in Japan, II, 1948 May
    - Post-War Developments in Japanese Education, I, 1952 April
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) (Box 3)
  - United States Education Mission to Japan, 1946
    - General
    - Correspondence
    - Memorabilia
    - Memoranda
    - Personnel
    - Press notices
    - Report of the United States Education Mission to Japan
      - Preliminary material
      - Mimeographed copies
      - Printed copies
      - Press copies
  - United States Education Mission (Second) to Japan, 1950
  - Vining, Elizabeth Gray, tutor to the Crown Prince of Japan